[Music]
n
w
[Music]
hello hello I think I'm audible
now okay I guess I'm audible now
apologies for that but let me once again
greet you all geopolitical dub Shia
Singh YK Noel Sony S of cha gorav tandan
Ajit abishek minini Goku priyan hello
Arian Sharma Ro radman Freeman Cosmic
joke joke ishan sanal Gio Barat space
asphalt vikash HPS shorts Ajit gorov
tandan sain Kumar abishek palia Hayden
Harvey curious guy feminist Slayer hello
Tas hello sir threat Ripper AES digpal
feminist Slayer rushil midra miir Kar
anurag Shia Singh YK Noel sidhant Anuj B
Patel rakit Mo Prav K JY Phoenix aush
tinglu Omar D karik Prasad a random
right- Winger TR7 insane Omar D and
everybody else Monica AA leang wangi
prit Agarwal and everybody else so okay
uh uh let me stop at that otherwise I'm
going to spend the whole day doing that
so let's get started with the questions
and the comments and let's begin where
are we let's take with the first one
this is by Samar and this is uh have
been involved in something or the other
and not able to watch your streams like
I used to before however just want to
appreciate you sir for being so active
on so many podcasts and also answering
our questions despite the busy schedule
uh all that thank you so much and thank
you so much ra ramal lakmi G for being
so consistent with the time stamps it
helps a lot yes well summer thank you so
much I am going to do more of this these
live stream
and I really appreciate what ramal lakmi
does every time you know putting up the
time stamps it's it really helps the
audience it also helps me because I
don't have to make the time stamp so
thank you ramal lakmi and thank you
Samar let's get on with the next
question okay these are two questions
about the same topic the one is by
Pierre namaskar are we headed towards
World War II how do you see this Israel
Iran situation finally play out in the
end uh thank you Tech facts gaming 24
says can the recent Iran Israel conflict
combined with the Russia Ukraine war
even the Armenia aeran conflict Etc
escalate into World War II is it is what
it seems all right so the main question
is are we headed towards the Third World
War World War I and obviously we have a
major flash point which is the Iran
Israel situation and a lot has happened
so it all depends on a number of factors
also there's the Russia Ukraine conflict
which is which has been going on for
more than two years and there's the
situation Armenia aeran turkey and much
more in which India is also involved to
some extent extent in supporting Armenia
which Iran is also doing and so on so a
lot going on so first of all let's take
a look at the map of the region because
that kind of helps us understand the
world where's the map here is the map so
here's the map and this is the region
which is the flash point so we have this
tiny little country called Israel if you
can see here that's where Israel is here
we have Iran these two nations are
separated by almost roughly 2,000
kilometers 2,000 kilomet of separation
and they are kind of in a state of
hostility not war hasn't been declared
but they have launched strikes and
counter strikes at each other and that's
a concerning situation definitely very
concerning so there is that going on and
that's currently an open conflict then
we also have the situation in Ukraine as
we know I mean I don't have to introduce
the matter here everybody knows what's
happening there Russia is in control of
roughly about a fourth or a fifth of the
territory of Ukraine and Russia has the
upper hand from the way everything is
going so all of that and obviously the
Armenia aeran issue over here this is
the region between the Caspian and the
black seas in the Caucasus region so all
of that
could this lead to World War I is the
question now what does it depend on it
depends on whether the Israel Iran
conflict escalates whether the uh Gaza
situation escalates and other players
get involved a World War means multiple
Nations especially the most important
and Powerful nations are involved that's
a World War situation the last time we
had it was during the European Tribal
wars which is called World War I and
World War II which is essentially the
same conflict the continuation of the
same conflict with a with a brief a
couple of decades in between that was
that's what it was so the current
situation let's talk about the Gaza
situation it's kind of under control uh
Hamas is the force that is that has that
launched this terrorist strike on Israel
on the 7th of October last year
23 and Israel has retaliated massively
it's kind of devastated Gaza uh there is
a lot of unease among the Arabic Nations
that that surround Israel because of
this because the they are their
sympathies are with Palestine even
though they don't want to have
Palestinians on their territory but yeah
their sympathies are with Palestine so
there is a lot of uh stress on these
nations because of the domestic
sentiments so Israel has to calibrate
its responses and its actions in such a
way that it doesn't offend uh its
neighbors too much otherwise there could
be you know problems then there is
hisbah which let's go back to the map
isbah is is located in southern Lebanon
North of Israel and that is a situation
now Iran kind of controls hisbah and
Hamas Hamas and hisbah are said to be
Iranian proxies there is a situation in
Yemen with the huis who are also Iranian
proxies and Iraq has a significant Shia
population and lots of Iranian assets
there as well but the problem is if Iran
and Israel are in a state of conflict
they have a significant distance between
the two Nations around 2,000 kilometers
how so how do they fight a war they can
fight a war via proxies Israel doesn't
really have Proxes in the region Iran
does so that way it's Advantage Iran and
Iran has lots of missiles and drones and
all of that which can use to Target
Israel the Israelis can Target they have
good aircraft Iran doesn't have good
aircraft it has old aircraft the Tom
Cats and all that Israel has good
aircraft modern aircraft it has the
f-16s it has f35s and some other
aircraft as well which it can use to
Target Iran but it will need refueling
lots of complications so it's really
hard for these two Nations to go to war
very hard but if Israel does succeed in
targeting Iranian uh nuclear facil fac
facilities then Iran could be could want
to re retaliate to that and then we
could see escalation but as of now it
doesn't look like this conflict could
escalate and lots of more Nations could
get involved
there's always the possibility but right
now it doesn't look like that so the
Hamas strike the Hamas terrorist attack
on Israel happened October
723 uh Israel kind of blames Iran for
that so so Israel then bombed the
Iranian Consulate in Damascus Syria
consulate which is a diplomatic property
and it's illegal under international law
Israel did that and they killed a couple
of high ranking Iranian generals so
that's what Israel did now Iran went
ahead and responded to that by launching
this massive strike on uh Israel with
ballistic missiles perhaps cruise
missiles also a bunch of drones uh and
this strike showcased a fraction of
Iran's capabilities in this regard but
most of the missiles and all that were
kind of neutralized and other actors
were also in play uh Saudi Arabia Jordan
Etc helped in taking down some of these
missiles and drones
so that's what happened then Israel has
again responded with a couple of with a
few strikes on Iranian soil and now it
looks like Iran may let it slide because
there's not been apparently too much
damage and things can be contained so
that is where we are today strikes
counter strikes retaliation counter
retaliation but right now it looks like
things could possibly perhaps and
hopefully simmer
down that's how it is today and if
things go and if things escalate is
really bad for the region because you
could see the closure of the closure of
the straight of hormos from which a lot
of the world's energy comes in or energy
pet petroleum products and all that
which could you know see oil prices
shoot up and that would not be good for
the world's economy especially for India
as
well so that's where we are today I
don't see World War II happening right
now I don't see the situation escalating
into World War I it's a tense situation
dangerous situation a single a simple
miscalculation could lead to a wide
under
conflict so one hopes that sane and cool
Minds Prevail but I don't see this
situation escalating into a major
conflict right now um and obviously the
Israel the the Ukraine situation exists
which is obviously a problem it's kind
of a long War kind of scenario the
Israel the the Ukraine situation Russia
has the upper
hand uh but that also seems to be kind
of contained right now there is talk
among NATO members of putting NATO boots
on the ground in Ukraine which would be
a major escalation and not a very wise
thing to do hopefully it doesn't happen
the Armenia aeran conflict which also in
involves turkey it also involves Iran it
has Russian Russian angle as well maybe
an Indian angle as well but that is a
small localized conflict and uh that
also can't lead to hopefully a larger
configration so overall right now the
way things stand I don't see the chance
of World War I IM
you know I don't see it happening uh
anytime soon hopefully I don't see it as
an imminent threat but yes the tension
levels geopolitical tension levels
globally are much higher than what it
what they were compared to let's say the
very beginning January 1st 2022 much
higher right now and it's the know the
the tensions are slowly gradually
escalating slowly so not a good
situation overall but right now I don't
see World War I happening
right next
question okay this is by panage Bora
after attacking the Iranian Embassy and
neglecting the sovereignty of other
countries the US has put sanctions on
Iran instead of Israel is it not
hypocrisy and what should India do now
and also talk about the future of the
imch okay multiple questions yes you're
right the
Israelis bombed the Iranian Consulate in
Damascus Syria which is a clear
violation of international law now
imagine if every nation which has bad
relations with other nations imagine all
these nations start taking out each
other's consulates and and embassies
imagine what would happen then complete
breakdown of the global order complete
chaos lawlessness and Wars everywhere so
we can't have such a thing happening so
the Israelis went ahead and did this and
there was no condemnation from the West
none at all now I am not anti-israel or
pro-israel or whatever I don't have a
horse in this race I'm just
saying this as a neutral external
Observer of course we in India have
sympathies with with Israel Israel let's
you know we can say is a good friend of
India and vice versa but you can't have
this happen you can't do that but they
did this and there was no condemnation
from the West now isra now Iran goes
ahead and retaliates to that and and
launches missiles and drones and whatnot
at Israel most of which are taken down
and there's immediate
condemnation from the west from various
nations in the west and then the
Americans impose new sanctions on Iran
as if there's anything left I mean I
think they've already exhausted every
possible sanction you can think of you
know all the possibilities but they've
imposed new sanctions on Iran so yeah of
course it's hypocrisy you know there's
no consistency in these actions One
Nation does a bad thing you say nothing
The Other Nation does a bad thing you
condemn it and you impose sanctions you
got to have consistency you know but
that's not the way it is so the
so-called rules-based World Order is
actually a whims based World Order and
the US essentially is the nation that
decides what happens along with it with
its uh vasal in the west and other
places even in the
East and whatever they decide is Right
today is what happens tomorrow they may
take a totally different decision based
on what is best for them at that time so
it's entirely up up up to their
whims so that's not the kind of World
Order you need to have but that's just
how it works in geopolitics might is
right so yes hypocrisy is it of course
it is hypocrisy what should India do now
well India should stay out of this
matter not our fight not our problem
stay out of it India needs to just tell
the these nations that calm down stop
fighting go to the negotiation table do
diplomacy go sit sit down and and talk
it out find a diplomatic solution find
a you know uh negotiated solution
instead of fighting each other that's
what India should say that's obviously
always been India's stand consistent
stand on this matter what about the
future of the imech what is the imch
let's go to the map where's the map
here's the map the imch is the India
middle east Europe trade and economic
and connectivity Corridor so this is
something that was announced at the
during the uh G20 Summit in New Delhi
last year October I think it was in New
Delhi and um this is a connectivity
project that will connect India to the
Middle East to West Asia via sea and
then this uh Corridor or project will go
via Saudi Arabia into Jordan through
Israel in into Greece and there'll be
like there'll be a sea route you know
shipping lanes will be there shipping
channels there'll be Railway channels as
well there'll be Road channels as well
and so on so it essentially connects
India Via West Asia to Europe and the
gateway to Europe is Greece bypassing
turkey and this was supposed to start
actually the Saudis wanted this to hit
the ground running they wanted to to
start the construction of of this
Corridor within 45 days of the G20
Summit
but this problem happened this sudden
situation erupted in West Asia which is
the Gaza conflict and because of that
nothing has happened this project is
currently kind of stalled it's not
progressing forward because of the
entire situation in the Middle East so
that is the deal right now if the imch
corridor goes ahead it will be great it
will be kind of uh you could say uh an
alternative to China's more or less you
know moribund defunct uh belt and Road
initiative the you know the the one one
road to rule them all that sort of thing
so construction of this project and
operationalizing it would take about a
decade or so so we not even started
right now so that is a situation that is
unfortunate but that's where we are and
that's all because of the conflict the
Middle East tensions and
conflict okay v m says two years later
with the war stuck this looks ridiculous
clearly the Russian military was
unprepared for high-intensity Warfare
given how terribly they have
performed okay okay so were the Russians
unprepared and has there been this high
intensity conflict in Ukraine and how
have they performed terribly look at the
situation on the map okay here's the map
once again and we have Ukraine over here
in the middle of your screen yes and the
entire dbas
region is under not the entire region
but significant portions of the donbas
region are under Russian control Russia
has annexed these four
territories and the ukrainians have lost
tremendous amounts of Manpower they are
recruiting middle-aged men into their
Armed Forces they are even recruiting
pregnant women into their Armed
Forces uh their fighting strength is
gone the only reason they are still
fighting is because the West is
supplying Ukraine with weapons and
ammunition ammunition and weapons and
weapon systems and money
that's the only reason Ukraine is still
fighting their entire population male
population has been devastated and the
West has been saying that Russia is
losing from day one they have been
saying that Russia has run out of
ammunition two years ago they were
saying that one year ago also they were
saying that they were all they've been
saying for the past two years that
Russia is on the brink of losing this
war they have been saying that Putin has
cancelled and he's got three months to
live all kinds of these statements have
been made but where are we today who
controls what is Russia performing badly
are there Ukrainian or NATO soldiers on
Russian territory or do you have Russian
soldiers on what used to be Ukrainian
territory and is there high intensity
Warfare what are you talking about what
high-intensity Warfare there is a long
slow War situation scenario that we are
seeing right now and the Russians are
advancing step by step and they want to
they want this to last as long as
possible that's what it looks like right
now because the longer it lasts the more
the Ukrainian military gets depleted the
more the Ukrainian Manpower gets
depleted and at the end of the day
what's going to happen let me tell you
right now Ukraine is going to get
partitioned along a certain line what
line that's going to be is going to
depend on the Russians at what stage do
they say that that we are fine now we
are satisfied their initial objective
like they had said was to den naify
Ukraine and to demilitarize Ukraine and
they want Ukraine to be neutral which
means a regime change in Kiev which
means Mr zinski needs to go and live in
in the the us if he can So eventually
that's going to be the objective from
the Russian perspective as long as there
is a pro West government in Ukraine
which happened after the maidan Euro
Maan Revolution which was a coup a
regime change operation by by the US it
was not Mr zinski who came to power then
it was a different person but zalinsky
came to power what which year was it
2018 2019 somewhere around that time you
can look it
up so they will need a regime change the
the Russians will require a regime
change and they will partition Ukraine
along a certain line maybe it will be
along the naiper river maybe somewhere
else but Ukraine is going to be
partitioned so Russia is winning here
okay they haven't overrun Ukraine they
had that military on the outskirts of
Kiev in the very beginning in the first
half of 2022 and they withdrew it
because you know uh certain uh certain
uh agree I mean I mean what do you call
it because the certain promises were
made from the west but then those
promises were immediately rolled back
the moment the Russians also pulled back
from the outskirts of KV but that's how
it goes long story Ukraine is a disaster
Zone Russia has the upper hand Russia is
going to win this now you can be swayed
by Propaganda and repeat propaganda
whatever you read you can regurgitate
that but if you actually look at the
situation on the ground and analyze it
you will see that Russia has is winning
and Russia will win this war Ukraine is
a disposable asset for the West they are
not a member of the EU they're not a
member of NATO it's a disposable asset
this is a proxy war between NATO which
is the US and Russia and the proxy is
Ukraine Ukraine's manpow not woman even
woman power these days is the curent F
and Russia actually has got stronger
after this of course the sanctions and
all have but whatever I Russia is going
to win this okay the writing is clear
the writing is on the wall Russia is
going to win this and they will decide
at what point the conflict ends and in
which manner the conflict ends it's
going to end on Russia's terms not on
Ukraine's terms or NATO's terms there
you have
it V PAB says is Europe heading for a
war in the coming years well if you if
you ask the West if you ask the Western
media yes ukra Europe is another threat
of War because Putin wants to swallow
let's let's once again take a look at
the map according to them Putin is a
madman and Putin wants to First Take
Over Ukraine and then he will take over
mova then he will take over Romania and
he will take over Poland and Lithuania
lvia Estonia and then he will March
westwards and take Hungary and and so on
according to the West Putin is a Madman
who wants to take over the whole of
Eastern Europe maybe even more and he
wants to reestablish what he used to
something like the USSR that's what the
West would like to tell you but that's
not the case Putin has been extremely
restrained even in the war in Ukraine
the special military operation uh
there's been lots of provocations on
Russia terrorist attacks like the recent
attack uh Kus attack in Moscow and all
but they have not responded to that they
have been very very measured they have
been
very uh yeah measured is the right word
they have been very restrained the
Russians
and all they want the way I see it is
that Ukraine should become should no
longer be a threat a proxy threat for
Russia I don't see the Russians having
any interest in taking over you know
other other nations like the ones you
you see on the uh left half of the map
Poland Romania Hungary the Baltic
Nations and so on and so forth the
Baltic nations may be a interesting
piece of real estate but there you have
it so I I don't see so the only nation
that could plunge Europe into a war in
the coming years is Russia I don't think
Russia has the appetite for that Russia
is a great defensive power nobody can
intrude into Russian territory and try
to Annex any parts of Russia that'll be
uh well that's the last thing they'll do
Russia has a great defensive power they
have the world's largest nuclear Arsenal
nobody can dare to touch Russia but they
are not a great offensive power they
don't have the those offensive
capabilities that's why they have been
you know pursuing this slow war strategy
in Ukraine so if
Russia is
not a threat to Europe and Russia has no
intentions of taking over Europe then
who's going to fight who's going to
cause a war in Europe are are Germany
and France going to fight each other is
I mean that's not possible because they
are all members of NATO and the EU and
Western Europe essentially is under us
domination the real power in Western
Europe is the US not Germany not France
not the UK these are all under the US
thumb so there's no chance the way I see
it of uh any major war in Europe in the
coming years unless Putin is actually a
madman and I don't I don't think he is
he's a very rational and sane person so
I do not see Europe heading for war in
the coming years
nope okay what's next next this is by
akanga sakam I know from my working
experience with British and Americans
how much they hate Modi then why don't
they instrument regime change in India
given that they are so powerful uh PS
I'm just playing Devil's Advocate I
support Mr Modi and would never want
India to fall back with a puppet
government uh it's not that they hate
Modi as such they see Mr Modi and they
see the current government as a huge
obstacle for them towards making India
turning India India into another Japan
look at the way look at what Japan is
today Japan is not a Sovereign Nation
yes they have their own prime minister
they have their own Parliament they have
their own laws and all so it looks like
everything is fine they have their own
Navy and Army and Military you know
Defense Forces but if you look a little
deeper you will see that there is no
sovereignty in Japan there are more than
130 US military bases on Japanese soil
and the Japanese they have no say in
that the Japanese Constitution was by
the US and so on so forth Japan is not a
Sovereign Nation neither is South Korea
neither is Germany not even Italy okay
so you have to understand what
sovereignty is India is a Sovereign
Nation and India does not tow the
Western
Line the West would like to see India
become a market for them not a producer
of goods but a consumer of goods and
services coming in from the West they
want India to open up its Market there
should be no trade and tariff barriers
and India should do whatever they say
and India should impose sanctions on
Russia and India should go along with
the Western policies uh with the US's
policies on Ukraine and Russia and
everything else India should be a great
uh uh bulwark against China a great
counterbalance to China and ideally
India should
also have American Military presence on
its territory and India should become
more liberal which means India should uh
allow more India should allow Western Ng
to set up shop in India and do whatever
religious and other things they want to
do conversions and whatnot India should
just become a puppet like Japan that's
what they would like to happen that's
what they would like to see happen and a
strong government in India especially
the the BJP government government the
Modi government is not going to let this
happen India is getting stronger
now because of the last 10 years of
economic growth and the reforms and all
that that's a big problem so they don't
hate Modi
personally but they would like to see a
weak coalition government come to power
in India that's what they would like to
see and that is as good as a regime
change because when you have a weak
coalition government non BJP coalition
government then there will be I'm not
saying which party does what but you
know there's a lot of Western
fingerprints allegedly in certain
alleged political parties allegedly okay
so if a coalition government comes to
power with multiple parties vying for
Supremacy with multiple parties
allegedly having Western fre
fingerprints Etc in them then here you
go then there's no need to do a regime
change that itself is a regime
change uh so it's not that easy to do a
regime change in India if you had a a
nation with a dictator in place easy to
do a regime change but certain nations
are simply not uh the situation is
simply not conducive for a dictatorship
or a military coup India is one of them
so it's really hard so what you can do
if you are the West is you can fund
certain political parties you can also
allegedly create new political parties
and you can also allegedly fund certain
politicians and make them rise to
prominence and so on so it's a long-term
matter and I'm sure they're allegedly
doing that allegedly all right yeah so
it's not like they're not trying but
it's hard India is is is a hard nut to
crack okay couple of questions one is
from geopolitical dub and one is from
rodit sarar can there a military
alliance between India and asan just
like us in in Europe's NATO because our
interests and threats are common and
rudrajit says you have said that every
International Group must have a big dog
to run smoothly and efficiently it's
very true in the case of NATO the
European Union the Shanghai cooperation
agreement the Commonwealth of
independent states the CIS and so
on is there any big dog in
asan a group that's proven itself to be
quite
successful so
asan is the association of Southeast
Asian
Nations uh let's go to the map and see
what are these Southeast Asian nations
in case you may not be aware where's the
map here is map the Southeast Asian
nations are Myanmar Thailand Malaysia
Singapore Indonesia Cambodia Vietnam
Thailand Laos and the Philippines and in
case Vietnam I I did say Vietnam and I
hope I've not missed anything out if I
have
missed anything apologies in advance but
there you have it these nations I think
it's seven or eight Nations or maybe
nine or maybe seven you can look it up
the details so asan is not a military
Alliance it's an economic grouping of
Nations so what kind of grouping asan is
or SEO is or NATO is depends on the
Constitution or the chart the founding
Charter the agreements that everybody
signs when the the organ organization of
grouping is
instituted so so NATO is a military
Alliance that is how it is it was
founded that's what its Charter says
that's uh what the agreements say but
asan is an economic grouping of Nations
it's not an
alliance so when you have a an economic
group grouping of Nations it cannot form
a military alliance with anybody it's
simply an economic grouping there's no
military Dimension to it at all okay so
NATO and asan are very different even
Sark we have this defunct organization
called Sark well it's just it's the
South Asian Association for regional
cooperation so it's about cooperation
economic cooperation trade whatnot but
no military angle to it so that's how it
is so there can no there cannot be a
military alliance between India and asan
because asan is not a military Alliance
it's an economic grouping of Nations um
so taking rit's question now uh yes
every International grouping of Nations
multilateral grouping of Nations needs
to have a big dog to run smoothly and
efficiently NATO is a good case who
dominates NATO it's the US the European
Union is a good case who dominates the
European Union a non-european nation the
US what about the SEO Shanghai
cooperation organization the major
Nation the dominates it and is kind of
the leader so to say they would like to
be the leader is China the Commonwealth
of independent states the leader the
major Nation the top dog like you would
say is Russia what about Asia well asan
is kind of like the European Union in in
the sense that there is a non Asian
nation that dominates asan and that is
the United States none of the Asian
nations are powerful militaries or
powerful economies they were some of
them were called the Asian tigers in the
1990s and then there was the 97 event
which kind of killed that growth and
momentum
so there are no major Powers here there
are certain large economies but nothing
very large like India or
China so the major top dog is actually
the US which dominates
asan and yeah that's that's the thing
that's
answer let's take some questions okay
two questions by rodit
sarar the first one is why did SAR fail
but asan on the other hand has served
its purpose secondly we all know that
Pakistan's non-cooperative activities
are one of the prominent reasons behind
sark's failure can we kick Pakistan out
will it help Sark run more effectively
and
efficiently so why did Sark fail very
simple because of Pakistan you you you
have this nation a terrorist nation in
Sark and uh if you look at Sark it's the
nations of the Indian subcontinent and
the two largest most populous and most
powerful Nations and largest economies
are India and Pakistan I think Pakistan
is still the second largest economy
within SAR has Bangladesh eclipsed
Pakistan I'm not sure if it has an
apologies but yeah but at least when
when SAR was founded India and Pakistan
were the two largest
economies so when the two largest
nations within an organization within a
grouping of Nations simply can't get
along and that that grouping of Nations
essentially fails and India in the last
few years especially since Mr Modi came
to power has adopted this uh
policy of neglect of
Pakistan we will not talk to Pakistan we
will not do trade the Pakistani
themselves unilaterally ended trade
relations with India in 2019 if I'm not
mistaken and so India has uh adopted
this policy of completely neglecting Pak
istan we'll not talk to them we'll not
do trade we'll do nothing with them
we'll not even acknowledge we'll barely
acknowledge their existence we'll have
the minimum diplomatic ties you know
consulates and embassies and all but
nothing more than that that's it end of
story so when you have that sort of
relationship between two countries and
entirely because of Pakistan's fault we
didn't do that we didn't create the
situation we didn't send terrorists
across the border into Pakistan they
they are the ones doing that they've
been doing that for decades so that is
why Sark failed and why do we need to
revive Sark let it exist on paper India
can
pursue uh its interests bilaterally with
all these nations so when it comes to
let's say Sri Lanka let's go to the map
once
again when it comes to Sri Lanka India
can pursue bilateral relations excellent
bilateral relations with Sri Lanka or
with Bangladesh or Bhutan or Nepal or
whoever else or
Afghanistan we don't need to do it
multilaterally we can do it it
bilaterally so there is no real need to
you know kick Pakistan out and revive
SAR what's the point and I'm not even
sure what is the procedure for ejecting
a nation from a multilateral
organization each multilateral
organization will have its own rules I
don't know what the procedure is for
Sark but there's no need to go through
all that you know all that uh tedious
red tape and all that just India should
just engage with all the nations
bilaterally may be trilaterally in some
cases and there's no need to have this
forum like SAR so that's the reason why
we are not Reviving Sark and we are not
having any more Sark Summits or any of
that we just don't need that so Sark is
essentially kind of a defunct moribund
organization and it's fine that
way okay next
question Samar Gandhi says what's your
take on the geopolitics of the space
race going nuclear I'm not just talking
about nuclear space weapons but also the
plans of a nuclear power plant on the
moon meanwhile India is working on
nuclear powered rockets for space
missions India and Russia uh will be
working on a fusion reactor as well okay
space and nuclear power or nuclear
weapons uh in the 20th century the us at
least I remember had conducted nuclear
uh tests in space so you canate
obviously a nuclear weapon in space we
see nuclear reactions all over space all
the stars are nuclear reactions Fusion
reactions so uh you can detonate nukes
in space and you can well certainly you
can even have you know put nukes in
orbit and you can use space if you want
to as a place from where you can launch
nukes onto a nation but I think it's a
forbidden under various International
treaties so nobody has done that as far
as we know so nobody has deployed
nuclear in space as far as we know uh so
that's that uh what about nuclear power
plants on the moon yeah it can happen
certainly
feasible uh you can certainly uh see
nuclear nuclear reactors are pretty
large machines lots of different
components and it's essentially
about using heat to turn a a steam
engine a steam turbine that's actually
what a nuclear reactor is so uh
you can certainly set one up on the moon
you would have to transport all of that
equipment to the moon and you know
assemble it and set it up all there but
yeah these days you have smaller
reactors small modular reactors you have
small reactors that are small enough to
place them in submarines that's what
nuclear submarines are certain Nations
have those technology have that
technology the US
Russia France China India UK Etc have
nuclear
submarines those are reasonably small
small reactors obviously very heavy
reactors but yeah we have the US
especially has very powerful Rockets
Space X has very powerful Rockets so you
can certainly transport a nuclear
reactor to the moon for sure and it can
happen so uh so that's not a
geopolitical thing having a reactor on
the moon which will generate electricity
of course you would need water for that
there is water on the moon but there's a
lot of logistical stuff you you to
actually lots of log logistical problems
you to solve first before you can have a
working nuclear reactor on the moon but
it can be done but the geopolitics comes
when you talk about nuclear weapons and
as far as we know nobody has placed
nuclear weapons in Earth's orbit and I'm
sure it's forbidden according to various
you know International treaties but yes
it can happen and you don't know I mean
there are lots of secret spy satellites
and secret satellites being launched
and we don't know what they contain so
it's possible that there could be
nuclear weapons in space it's not out of
the realm of
possibility so it can be done and when a
nation is really powerful powerful
enough when you are a superpower you can
actually do it and nobody will know and
even if they know there's nothing people
can do like for example somebody asked
earlier that when Israel bombed the
Iranian Embassy there was no
condemnation no sanctions but when Iran
retaliated the US put sanctions
additional sanctions on Iran so when you
are the only superpower the most
powerful nation in the world you can do
whatever you want and if you feel like
putting nuclear weapons in space you may
do that and there's nothing anyone can
do about it people other nations may not
even come to know about it so yeah so
every domain can be weaponized even
space can be weaponized it may happen it
may already have happened hopefully not
but yeah
okay krunal says in recent times some
experts and Navy officers in India have
said that we need that we need to build
new aircraft carrier but looking at our
submarine Fleet sometimes it feels like
we do not have enough of them what are
my views my views on this are
controversial lots of people
disagree My Views are that how many
aircraft carriers do we have I think we
have two I think that's enough aircraft
carriers are incredibly expensive
billions of dollars the American uh
aircraft carriers which are Super
carriers they typically cost between 10
to 15 billion dollar a piece the Indian
aircraft carriers would cost about three
to five to6 billion dollar that's a
tremendous amount of money first of all
okay huge amount of resources then an
aircraft carer needs security which
means you need to have a bunch of other
ships around it to provide it with
security it has its an aircraft carer
will have its own sec security as well
counter measures versus missiles and
whatnot but you will need an additional
Cordon of security measures which
typically comes with the escorting
vessels destroyers Etc and you typically
want at least one somebody in in the mix
to escort the aircraft carrier ideally
multiple submarines and aircraft
carriers are very enticing Targets in
time of in times of
War you take out your enemy's aircraft
carrier it's a gigantic victory for you
a huge moral boost and a
disastrous moral Downer for the
opponent and so much lethality is
concentrated on in one
vessel and the last time aircraft
carriers actually fought in a war an
actual war was the forland Islands war
which was kind of a one-sided War but
the last time you had aircraft carriers
involved in a contested environment with
roughly equal size you know equal
balance of power or whatever that was
probably in the second world war the
Battle of Midway and all that and lots
of aircraft were hit and sunk in
that so aircraft carriers are a good are
a great means to project power when you
are the strongest nation in the world
and everybody is scared of you and
nobody dares to you know try and try and
fight you that's where a come come in
very handy but when it comes to India
I don't think it's a I think two are
enough I don't think we need a third one
as of
now in the future if India becomes the
second most powerful nation in the world
it would make sense to have maybe three
more aircraft carriers to project power
across the vast Indian Ocean region take
a look at this huge
region so in the future if India out
matches China and becomes the second
largest second most powerful Nation
Maybe by 2050 or whenever at that point
in time it may make sense to have 203
more so maybe a call a decision can be
can be taken in mid 2030s or early 2040s
to have maybe two or three more aircraft
carriers but right now what India needs
is not concentrated lethality but
distributed
lethality what is lethality it's fire
power how do you measure a Navy's
lethality simple measure how many
missiles can you put out at Sea on any
given day and missiles are typically
placed on ships or submarines so if you
have this
enormous region of Maritime real estate
called the Indian Ocean you would
ideally want to distribute your
lethality along a very large area lots
of ships and Naval assets distributed
over a large amount of Maritime real ass
estate and each ship should have a
number of missiles the more missiles
your Navy can put out on any given day
the more lethal your Navy is but if a
significant amount of the Firepower is
just on one ship you are concentrating
your lethality instead of Distributing
it and that makes that ship a very
enticing Target for your enemies so the
smart thing to do is to distribute your
lethality over a wide area with a wide
number with a large number of very
different assets Destroyers
submarines uh whatever other missile
boats Corvettes and so
on that's ideally what you want to do
and the most dangerous ship in today's
Naval domain is the
submarine right now one again let me put
the map out there right now India is
conducting freedom of navigation
operations in the sea of sashtra or what
they call the Arabian Sea the Western
Indian Ocean some Geniuses will tell me
that this re this this region of marit
of the sea is the Arabian Sea it's not
the Indian Ocean so to them I would like
to say the Arabian Sea is part of the
Indian Ocean okay the Bay of Bengal is
part of the Indian Ocean the mosambi
channel is part of the Indian Ocean all
right that's a different thing why am I
teaching geography here so the Indian
Navy is conducting freedom of navigation
operations in the Western Indian Ocean
region near the Gulf of Adan near the
coast of Somalia and and so on now what
we see is the Indian destroyers and
helicopters and Air Force Assets in
operation and Indian Naval Commandos the
Marcos in operation what you don't
see is that there may be a submarine or
two also in the
mix and submarines are the deadliest of
all naval ships today they are very hard
to detect they are invisible you don't
see a submarine lurking over there and
they can launch all kinds of dangerous
weapons very dangerous very deadly
weapons of of course there are means
Ways and Means to try and detect
submarines we not go into that but
submarines are the most lethal asset a
Navy can have and India how many
submarines does does India have today I
don't even want to guess the number I'm
sure it is definitely less than 20 which
is
woeful India should have at least 50
submarines of various kinds including
some nuclear attack submarines and some
ballistic missile submarines nuclear
nuclear power and also regular
submarines India should have at least 50
because look at the amount of territory
India has to
uh
Patrol that that territory needs to be
free of enemies for India's national
security purposes so India needs more
submarines that's my opinion India needs
to distribute its lethality not
concentrate it because this ship looks
very massive and powerful and it gives
us a great ego boost that's okay your
ego is fine
but what India really needs is
distributed lethal lethality especially
hidden distributed lethality so we need
more submarines if you have $5 million
five billion dollar to throw around
throw them at submarines not more
aircraft carriers that's my view on this
matter and I'm sure certain experts will
disagree but that's
okay okay lots of questions from our
friend rudrajit today why do Indians
always think
that every good thing can be can only be
done in the west by the westerners and
no great thing can be done by Indians in
India look at when Mr adani became the
world's second richest person so many
Indians were badmouthing him but the
same didn't happen when Mr musk became
the world's richest person what's the
reason behind this and what's the
solution that's a good question yeah
Indians Indians love it when somebody
else in the west or wherever whatever
else is Rich they'll read they'll buy
books about Steve Jobs they'll buy books
about Elon Musk and they'll try to
emulate their strategies in their life
career and life trajectory and all that
and they idolize Mr musk and Mr Steve
Jobs and and Mr Bill Gates and whoever
else Mr Bezos Jeff Bezos and whatever
else and you try to you know learn from
their life but when it comes to Indian
entrepreneurs and business people who
become rich ah we have to badmouth them
they must have done something wrong
that's a typical Indian mentality
example of of of typical Indian
mentality what does this stem for from
so there is this view that has been
inculcated in India this attitude that
getting rich means you have done
something wrong that being wealthy is is
a
sin there are poor people in India how
dare you become
wealthy how dare you be wealthy when
there there is poverty in
India and in the 20th
century the entire you know poverty was
glorified socialism was
glorified uh being poor was glorified
the the hardworking poor person was the
hero in most Hindi
movies and typically the industrialist
or the business person the rich guy was
the villain I as a kid as a little kid I
saw all these amitab bachan movies in
which he's the he's either a kolie or
he's part of mazour union or whatever
and he's the good guy and these evil
industrialists are are exploiting the
poor mazur or the poor
workers so this uh so this brought in
this
mindset it inculcated it created this
mindset among Indians through these
repeated uh you know brainwashing
sessions that that movies are Bollywood
movies are that being rich is glorious
oh sorry being poor is glorious being
poor is is somehow Superior it makes you
Superior being poor is more dignified
than being rich and being rich
necessarily means that you are evil and
you are corrupt and you are
exploitative so you only see this among
Indians but when somebody outside India
is Rich Indians think that is a good
thing because they must have done it the
right way but when somebody in India
becomes rich there is this frog in the
well mentality you want to pull them
down and if something bad happens to
them people celebrate it's very
unfortunate you know what then shopping
said then shopping the former Chinese
Premier he said that being rich is
glorious and that's what try China is
trying to do so you can get
rich honestly can't
you you should get rich honest honestly
and today it's possible to get really
wealthy really rich through honest
means and if if more people get rich in
India the overall prosperity of the
country
increases and there is this view that
you know
only some people get rich and and then
the disparity between the rich and the
non-rich is increasing and that's why
the rich must be evil all these weird
stupid
absurd theories have become mainstream
in India and it's all programmed into
most Indians into the mindset of most
Indians that's why Indians hate it when
when Indians get rich but they celebrate
Rich foreigners so that's the reason the
solution is more Indians should get rich
that's the solution the more Rich
Indians we will have the less you know
slowly these attitudes will hopefully go
away but those of you who watch me
please understand being rich is a good
thing I want all of you to make as much
money as you possibly can and that will
help the country because if you get rich
you'll be able to generate more
employment you'll be able to help India
in your own way so it is glorious like
Den shapping said to be rich
and it doesn't mean that you are an evil
person so go ahead and make as much
money as
possible okay geopolitical dub says Shri
chingis Khan or his successor conquered
China it was Shri chingis Khan himself
of course his son also did but it was
all started by sh chingis Khan so Shir
chingis Khan conquered China and
established the Yuan Dynasty so so how
do the Chinese think about sharich
chingis Khan do they hate him do they
consider him an invader
the Chinese have very strange
relationship with Shri chingis
Khan so he was born in the
1270s 13th the the second half of the
13th century and it's in the first
quarter of the of the 14th century that
he unified Mongolia after Decades of of
struggle and he became the great
KH uh and then he decided to invade
China to in in in response to centuries
of Chinese meddling in Mongolia and
oppression of the
Mongols so he invaded China in the 1210s
I don't remember which year exactly and
uh there were two invasions the first
one uh
was okay I don't remember the dates you
can look look at the look the dates up
so the first Invasion happened before
chingis Khan invaded
quasm so his first foreign expedition
was to China he successfully conquered
large parts of China uh he defeated the
shisha Empire there were three dynasties
ruling various parts of China at the
time he defeated the he defeated the
Western Shia the
Shia and he made them his
wasal and he left then there was the
invasion of quasm in response to
atrocities done by the Turks who were
ruling Iran and quasm at the time on the
Mongols there was also successful
and then the Chinese rebelled so chingis
Khan ran back to China and conquered
China again and he sacked
Beijing so that is a deal and then
U during the second invasion of China he
died jingis Khan we don't know why he
died what happened but he died and then
his son ogai become became the Khan and
ogai continued the the conquest of China
and he established the the Yuan Dynasty
but then retrospectively chingis Khan
was declared the first emperor of the
Yuan Dynasty and then the third emperor
was Shri kubl Khan who was the grandson
of chingis Khan and he was a great
emperor of China and so and so forth
long story I'm not going to go into the
whole story but jingis Khan smashed
China
twice so and he established the Yuan
Dynasty which is which the Chinese call
a conquest Dynasty so what is the
relationship between China and Jing G
well on the one hand they obviously hate
the fact that this guy came and smashed
them twice defeated them flattened
Beijing they hate that so they they
tried to they have tried their best to
erase the memories of chingis Khan let
me give you an example uh let's bring
the map on the
screen
so when chingis
Khan uh conquered and captured
Beijing he let's let's uh put the
satellite imagery on the screen okay
this is a Terrain so where is Beijing I
lost Beijing oh there we are Beijing so
north of Beijing you have all these
mountains look here you have all these
mountains it's a very mountainous region
and Beyond the mountains to the north
you have the great desert the goby
desert and this is this great goby
desert is what protected Beijing from
nor Northern Marauders like the Mongols
but jingis Khan came to the
goby and he conquered Beijing and there
was a great battle between the Mongols
and the Chinese let me try and locate
the place if I can it is
called the Badger's mouth pass
yuling will I be able to locate it I
think it's here between two
Hills okay this is where it happened and
if you look at uh the satellite
imagery it's just you know
roads and uh a river and stuff this is
where that momentous battle happened in
which chinis Khan smashed the Chinese
Army and that L laid the road open for
him to go and take Beijing which he did
successfully and he flattened Beijing
and this here what you are seeing right
now between two mountains as you can see
is where the battle of the badger mouth
pass happened this region is called
yuling I believe this
place and do you see any Memorial or
anything the Chinese have not attempted
to commor commor commemorate that
battle they have tried to erase every uh
sign of that battle so there's nothing
there to see and down south is Beijing
which JIS Khan was able to take so uh
they have tried their best to erase
history the Chinese but on the other
hand my dear
friends okay let's go to the back to the
map on the other hand the Chinese make
territorial claims based on the extent
and conquests of the Yuan Dynasty the
Mongol Dynasty with chingis Khan
established so during the time of the of
the Yuan Dynasty when Shri kubl Khan the
grandson of chingis Khan was
ruling the Yuan Dynasty had a certain
kind of
relationship uh
with okay let me where are we with
Tibet so the relationship between the
Yuan between Yuan China and Tibet was
that of a guru and shisha Tibet was the
guru and the Mongols or the or the Yuan
Dynasty were the
shisha so the Tibetans taught the
Mongols Buddhism especially tantric
Buddhism
the the vajana I believe
Buddhism and in return the Mongols uh
gave protection to Tibet so Tibet was
kind of like a wasal but not really a
wasal you did not have Mongol boots on
the ground in Tibet but you could say
technically it was a wasal of the Yuan
Dynasty So based on that the Chinese
claimed Tibet and they conquered it and
based on that they are also trying to
claim parts of arunachal Pradesh and and
various other Indian territories based
on what they claim was the territorial
extent of the Yuan
Dynasty so on the one hand they hate
chingis Khan they want to erase every
trace of his
history on the other hand they make
territorial claims based on the
conquests and territorial extent of the
Yuan Dynasty which was not a Chinese
dynasty it was a Mongol Dynasty that
conquered
China so that's the weird relationship
they have with chingis Khan and the Yuan
Dynasty they hate the fact that they
were conquered they hate the fact that
the Yuan Dynasty ruled China for
significant amount of time they even try
to erase uh the the history of the Yan
Dynasty in inner Mongolia so inner
Mongolia is Southern Mongolia which is
Mongol territory but it is currently
under Chinese occupation okay so over
there people the people are mostly
Mongols and they are forced to learn the
Chinese language all education is in the
Chinese language I don't think they are
allowed they're allowed to learn uh you
know they I don't think they are allowed
to do their schooling in the Mongol
language and there is no mention of
chingis Khan in the curriculum and and
people are forbidden from uh celebrating
chingis Khan and his conquests and
celebrating his memory so yeah the
Chinese are kind of still afraid of
chingis Khan they certainly hate him but
they want to use the Yuan Dynasty's
territorial extent as the pre IND to
Annex territories which they did like in
Tibet and they want to claim more Indian
Territory based on that so that's the
weird relationship the Chinese have with
Shiri chingis Khan and the Yuan
Dynasty Tanya says I recently read the
Roman Revolution by Ronald Sim it talks
about the dangers of fascism and
oligarchy and that became both the death
Nell of the Roman Republic and the seed
of resurgence of of the Roman
superiority in in its sub continent or
region I've been wondering has autocracy
or dictatorship does it have any
benefits especially when it brings about
the development of her civilization and
the people in the modern day de is
democracy the best form of government or
would something like a strong autocracy
be beneficial especially in a country as
diverse as India and is it okay as a
rule to sacrifice some Liberty at the
altar of
development good question you know some
people claim that I support dictatorship
I don't like democracy that is absurd
that is nonsense I firmly believe in
democracy but an indigenous form of
democracy the kind of democracy we used
to have historically now going back to
this question what is superior does
autocracy have its benefits does
dictatorship have its benefits or should
we insist on Democracy only and what
form of
democracy can autocracy or dictatorship
bring about the development of the
civilization and its people and so
on well the answer is sitting right in
front of your eyes go back to the past
2,000 3,000 let's say 5,000 years of
Indian
history think back think about the times
when India was as at at its Pinnacle
economically militarily culturally Etc
what periods of time were
those the oldest is well one of the
oldest times we can think of is the the
rule of Lord Ram Shri Ram was he elected
democratically go back to the Ramaya the
the Mahabharat times was Lord Krishna
elected democratically is the king of
dwarka and whatever
else the morian
era when India was unified the entire
subcontinent was unified
politically and it was a time of of
great
prosperity in India and excellent
governance and all that where the Moran
Emperors elected
democratically where the Gupta Emperors
elected democratically where the kushan
Emperors elected democratically where
the mahak chatas of Western India
elected
democratically was chhatrapati shivaji
Maharaj elected democratically so on so
forth where the Chula Emperors elected
democratically these were the times when
India was as its at its highest when it
comes to Economic Development uh quality
of
life um and so on military uh you know
National Defense all those things
whenever you had these periods of great
prosperity and and all that you had
autocracies in power in India and the
same applies to the rest of the world do
you you can give me examples of the West
the West is democratic the US is a great
democracy and democracy has made them
succeed is it really a democracy a
two-party system which is one step above
the Chinese and North Korean one party
system and if you look at the US
democracy you will see that it doesn't
matter who wins the election and who
becomes president the policies don't
change whether it's the foreign policy
the the mil military policy or even
economic policies nothing changes it's
like the same party is ruling it doesn't
matter who's
President so is that really democracy a
two-party system which actually gives
you the same results who no matter who
comes to power
I mean Trump tried to make lots of
changes at the end of the day he
succeeded in doing nothing and nothing
changed in the way The American Nation
behaves Visa the rest of the
world so the US is actually an autocracy
disguised as a
democracy and you think democracy is
freedom of speech freedom of expression
look at what's happening in the US look
at look at what's happening in Canada
look at what can get you jailed in the
UK speech saying certain things can get
you jailed in the UK saying things where
is the freedom of speech so I'll tell
you what there's no real democracy
anywhere in the world the best example
of a good Dem of a real democracy is
India completely chaotic hundreds of
political parties but yeah that's what
democracy actually
is historically we had a hybrid system
we would have a king or an emperor at
the very top and you would have
democracy at at the grass roads so the
people in in the cities and towns and
Villages could would elect their own
officials who would
govern them and provide services and
interface with the higher authorities
that's the kind of democracy India had
democracy at the Grassroots you elect
your own leaders and
officials but at the top you don't get
to change anything that's how it used to
be and that's what worked for India
historically for thousands of years uh
Rome was obviously an autocracy it was a
always a dictatorship you had Republic
kind of thing in in yeah you had the
Roman Republic in which the people who
could cast votes were all
Nobles the common people could not cast
votes women could not cast votes and so
on so there's never been any real
democracy even what they call Greek
democracy only the nobility could cast
votes only men could cast votes there
was there was slavery in Greek democracy
there was slavery in American
democracy and so on so there is no
perfect system there is no real
democracy most democracies are only
masquerading his democracies at the end
of the day what do you want as a human
being you want a great quality of life
you want a great future for yourself and
for your
children you want to be able to progress
to the highest extent of your potential
you want your children to be able to
progress to the highest extent of their
potential and you want a great future
for your future
Generations do you care whether it comes
to democracy or autocracy whoever can
give it
best is fine what you think so I am not
against democracy India is the mother of
democracy that is what Mr Modi has said
many times and correctly so India is the
mother of democracy but we had our own
system our own form of democracy which
is not this fake form of democracy that
you see everywhere else just because you
can go and cast a vote somewhere doesn't
make that Nation a true
democracy so yeah historically for India
dictatorships and autocracies have
worked really well when you had good
rulers good Kings good good Emperors
good Queens whatever yeah but so you
need to balance it out
properly but what generally gives you
the best results and what get things
gets things done is a more autocratic
form of
government it's just a fact but yes
democracy is important because people
should have a say in what happens and
how the country is run
and uh yeah there you have
it RIT once
again why doesn't India develop the
lakshadweep islands archipelago like the
males it will help India to attract many
national and international tourists and
help India's tourism sector to grow even
further what's your opinion on this so
the luure Deep Islands once again we
have to go to the
map so in case you may not be aware the
lakad islands are
to are off India's western coast over
here this tiny Islands big bunch of
islands very small Islands most of them
all the way up to what's called
minoi and south of that is a
continuation of the same archipelago but
it's a different Nation it's called the
malds and it's a much larger territory
all the way down south and it
essentially culminates in the illegally
occupied
British Indian Ocean territory the chos
archipelago now the Maldives is a great
very famous tourist
destination many Indians have in the
past been to the Maldives excellent uh
facilities you get there five star
treatment I mean depending on how much
you want to spend and so on but when it
comes to the Le Islands which are just
as beautiful as the Maldives there's
hardly any tourism at all because India
has not bothered to develop the tourism
potential of the LX
Islands so what should India do about
this well obviously we should go ahead
and develop the tourist potential
tourism potential of the LX Islands the
problem is that in the lwe archipelago
there are fewer Islands than the
Maldives and most of these islands are
quite small so it's just a small number
of islands that have the potential to
become future tourist
destinations and uh there is a
population that lives on these islands
and they also have to be taken care of
you cannot simply transform the island
into a
resort so there are certain things but
the the point is that this should have
been done in the 20th century this
should have been done long ago we're
going to have to start now right now I'm
not even sure if you can take a flight
from Delhi or Kolkata or or Chennai or
or Mumbai to the L Islands I think
there's a flight somewhere from
somewhere in Kerala or something I may
be mistaken but as far as I know there
there's not too many flights there
there's only one air strip in the lak
that can take big airliners as far as I
know so all this needs to be first
addressed you need to have the uh
infrastructure to be that should that
would be that would enable lots of
tourists to come in then there should be
hotel and resource and other
infrastructure that can accommodate
large number of tourists and this has to
be done in a in a way that does not
disrupt the way of life of the people
who already live in this part of of
India the people who live on the islands
and so all of these factors have to be
taken into consider consideration so
India has thus far not done anything to
develop the tourist potential of of the
Le vience if this begins now it may take
five or 10 years at least to get things
going properly so my opinion is that we
should certainly develop the L Islands
into a major tourist destination they
are just as pretty just as beautiful as
the
Maldives so why send why why
why invest money in the Maldives why
spend money there spend money in your
own economy in the in the Indian economy
but we should be we should have the
opportunity to to do that for that you
need the development of this
infrastructure in the lak archipelago so
that as far as I know has not really
started we start now it'll take a while
5 10 years at least yeah so we should do
that I
agree okay I think all the questions are
from r r rodra jit sarar why didn't
Alexander expand into the Balkans in the
Italian Peninsula is good question yes
why didn't Alex why did Alexander go
eastwards instead of going westwards
okay let's take a look at the
map okay let's go westwards to Greece so
present day Greece is a small country
the historic Greek region included much
of Anatolia which is Turkey tury
K and uh yeah it was much
larger and some of it even included
parts of uh present day Italy so
Alexander was Macedonian which is a
Greek
ethnicity
and here's the deal see the the Balan
region the Balkans which is present day
Serbia Montenegro Bosnia heroina and
Croatia Etc the Balan region was well
known to the Greeks it is right next
door to Greece to Historic Greece so
there was nothing new to learn there it
was not interesting from the perspective
of of discovering new lands and new
people and new cultures it was already
known that's Point number one and the
same goes for Italy the Italian
Peninsula U the Italian Peninsula was
also reasonably well known to the Greeks
it is right next door and then the the
there's the factor of of Aristotle so
Aristotle the Greek philosopher was uh
the teacher of Alexander Alexander's
father was Phillip Philip of Macedonia
and Philip arranged this guy this
philosopher Aristotle as a tutor for his
son Alexander now Aristotle encouraged
Alexander to discover the world to the
east of
Greece and it is Aristotle's tutoring
and teachings that that Lit this fire in
in Alexander that I'm going to go and
conquer the world eastwards
and uh Aristotle encouraged
Alexander to be very let's say
ethnocentric in his
conquests treat Greeks the people of
Greece as your own people as your own
relatives as your own family and treat
non- Greek people the same way you would
treat animals and
plants and you will see this play
out in Alexander's Conquest brutal
Conquest very cruel
Behavior you know if you if you read uh
books about Alexander if you watch
movies about Alexander he's shown as
this great Noble conqueror you have no
idea how horribly brutal he was how
terribly cruel he
was in his
conquests he mercilessly slaughtered
entire cities the populations of entire
cities and Villages he crucified
thousands of people absolutely
unnecessary what he did and even his
activities in in the western regions of
India which he kind of touched were
brutal and and and
and very
cruel so it is because of Aristotle's
teachings that Alexander decided to go
eastwards instead of westwards or
anywhere else he decided to spend all
his energy into Conquering the East and
and reaching the end of the world
essentially and it worked well in Persia
he was able to conquer
Persia uh and then he he conquered par
parur they call they call it persis and
he got drunk and in his drunkenness he
ordered the entire city to be burned
down and you can still see The Scorch
marks today if you go to the ruins of
what they call parsa historically called
parur and what the West calls persis so
he conquered Persia and then he went
ahead westwards to conquer India and
that's where he failed long story short
it was all because of this guy Aristotle
that Alexander decided to go eastwards
instead of trying to conquer the Balkans
or Italy or whatever else all because of
Aristotle and his
takings curious Herald says Indus Valley
artifacts are being sold online why is
no one talking about it can we put a
stop to this I think I've spoken about
this a couple of years ago it's been a
long time maybe uh we
can I can bring this up again so what is
curious talking about let me put that on
the screen so that we understand what's
what is
happening so I've got
these okay let's take a look at all
these I've got a bunch of tabs open here
this is from the Tribune and this
article is from
2015 okay it's from the 15th of April
2015 it says rakari site being plundered
due to a lack of protection and whose
protection should be there the
archaeological Survey of India so lack
of official protection and the plunder
of treasure TRS hidden underneath by
unscrupulous elements are playing Havoc
with the 5,000 yearold ancient
archaeological site and so on that's
from 2015 let's look take a look at this
article from 2019 harapan site marauded
by treasure Hunters so even four years
later in 2019 this was going on and
they're talking about raki gari once
again can you see this raki
gari so there's this article now let's
see what we have here
this is a site called Edgar lan.com
okay it says art of the indust valley
and this is an online auction site so
this is a rare Indus Valley seal third
to 2 millennium BC and if you want to
order it you can order it online it will
cost you
$2,450 where did this guy Edward Edgar
loen procure this from and there's more
a rare Indus Valley cylinder seal more
cylinder seals
this is from Mahar once again sarasti
Hindu civilization Ira third millennium
BC a pot with
Bulls here you have a goblet here you
have a bow another there is a cup more
portter portr portr fish look at this
more ptry multiple vessels here you have
a figurin an idol and here you have
these uh human heads
more human heads more human heads this
is just one side this is see more
figures of human beings this looks like
a pin and mirror very rare very rare
this also is something like
that so this is this website called
Edgar lan.com now let's take a look at
another one this is
Barakat Barakat gallery.com and lots of
the same things over here similar things
over here you can see terra cotta Bulls
a bronze bull there's a canister there's
a shell which with incision with with
some kind of uh incisions on it there is
a Wessel there's all kinds of stuff over
here there's an other earwar tile and so
on and this this just the list just goes
on and on and on multiple Pages you can
see six seven eight pages this is
Barakat gallery.com here you have sues
which is a British famous British
auction site once again over here
they've got this Vaz from the sarasa
Hindu era of India's Indian civilization
then you have vasat
auctions you have stuff
from not sure where it is it is
obviously the same civilization same
same era then you have gandhar janapada
punch marked silver
coins and so on lots of Indian coins are
being auctioned over here then you have
something called Vatican do
and vatican.com
yeah is selling all
these all these artifacts from which is
Indian ancestral heritage from the Saras
Hindu
region so this is happening rampantly
it's I'm just I've just shown you a few
of these online auction sites now I'm
not saying all of this is coming from
rakar okay don't get me wrong some of it
may have come from rakari but there are
many other
sites in India in what is temporarily
Pakistan there are lots of sites and it
is possible that much of this may be
coming from the Pakistani side of the
Border because over there they don't
really care about the culture they don't
really care about their ancestral
heritage the Saras Hindu Heritage so
they may be open to selling everything
off to the West so maybe much of it may
be coming from Pakistan but some of it
obviously is also coming most likely
from India
and that is a travesty this is our
ancestral heritage thousands of years
ago our ancestors made all of these
artifacts this is our Priceless
ancestral civilizational heritage which
is being sold off auctioned off online
it will be put in various collectors
collections some people may use it as an
ashtray some people may use it for for
whatever else it is infuriating but but
nothing is being done what needs to be
done is that at least the archaeological
Survey of India should have the decency
to properly protect the sites that are
officially under its
protection and that's not happening I
promise you the ASI is not doing its
work so that is my main problem I don't
care I mean there's nothing we can do
about what the pakistanis do with our
heritage that's under their control
right now but at least what's within
India the majority of the archaeological
sites of the sarasti Hindu era of our
history are in India not in Pakistan
so at least we can do what we can to
safeguard Our Heritage and the ASI is
not doing its job properly that's the
real problem what can I do to what can
we do to to put a stop to this the ASI
needs to get its act together the
government needs to take the ASI to task
that's what needs to happen maybe
someday it will happen while we still Al
alive hopefully we'll
see really
infuriating okay DJ funhub says wo a
curious question how do you find eye
color hair color or just any color just
by looking at some
bones okay so yeah I know what the
person is referring to when you find
ancient uh ancient human remains from
let's say 5,000 years ago 10,000 years
ago 4,000 years ago whatever you can
actually determine what that person
looked like you can reconstruct what the
person looked like not just the shape of
the face and all that but also the color
of your skin color of your eyes the
color of your
hair and we know that the ancient skians
the Shaka
people we know obviously based on the
skeletons how tall and how sturdy or
whatever or not they were but we also
know what color the skin had what color
the eyes had and color the hair had the
skians were
typically light brown they would
typically have light brown skin not
white skin but light brown skin skin
dark eyes brown eyes typically and dark
hair the yam also were not white people
they had light brown skin they dark eyes
and and and dark hair so how do we know
this we can't tell just by looking at
some bones you have to extract DNA from
the from those bones and ensure that DNA
is not contaminated by touching it with
your with your fingers or hands it has
to be done
properly so you take the bones you EX
extract DNA from it and if the bones are
found in a cold part of the world then
it's easier to extract DNA and so you
extract the DNA you sequence the DNA and
then you find the genetic markers which
tell you what color the skin the eyes
the hair
are okay so that's how you do it you
can't tell eye color hair color skin
color just by looking at bones you do it
by extracting DNA and finding the
genetic
code which tells you what skin color eye
color hair color it is it's through
genetics not by just looking at bones
that you do
this sair Kazi says whom did Lord
Krishna serve in the
Mahabharat and I was reading about the
Mahabharat and I realized that even Lord
Krishna did not choose the path of
idealism during
war then what then what stopped our so
called so-called great leaders to use
any means necessary to do to do the
light right thing
well you ask very good questions my dear
friend uh first of all whom did Lord
Krishna serve in the
Mahabharat well we call Lord Krishna
Paras sari sari means charioteer and Par
was obviously one of the names of Arjun
the great warrior so Lord Krishna during
the war was the charioteer of
Arjun he drove the Chariot that carried
Arjun into battle
so did he serve Arjun well that act of
of of being the charer is actually you
can say its service to Arjun he was
serving Arjun in battle by being his
charer did so to a certain extent he was
serving Arjun in that specific role as a
charioteer secondly he was also fighting
on the side of the pandavas so you could
say that by fighting on the side of the
pandas he was serving the pandas to
certain extent so he was serving Arjun
you know to a certain extent he was
serving the pandas to a certain
extent but who was really serving well
actually he was serving the cause of
Dharma and he was he was
serving the
civilization because by defeating the
the the adies the
coras you were serving Dharma and you
were taking the the civilization the
nation so to say there was no Nation at
the time India was much greater than a
nation India has always been a
civilization
state so he was serving the civilization
the the Indian civilization the the
bhattia civilization he was serving bhat
worsh and its people that's what he was
truly serving by doing these things so
his service was not really to to Arjun
or to the pandas it was to
bhatar as a civilization State and it
was to Dharma the concept of
righteousness so that
is whom Lord Krishna served in the
mahabharath the second question is about
um even Lord Krishna did not choose the
path of idealism during the war so what
stopped our so-called great leaders from
using any means necessary to do the
right thing yeah good question so there
are there are U examples incidents
during during the Mahabharat War when
Lord Krishna kind of you could say
cheated a a little bit of cheating
but it's okay to cheat in war as long as
you are on the right side if as long as
your objective is
good if there let's say you have a very
cruel despicable enemy who is a
genocidal
Barbarian then should you fight
according to the rules of warfare or
should you do anything that's necessary
to defeat that that enemy that opponent
because if you don't defeat the opponent
that person will ravage your
civilization and do unspeakable things
to its people obviously it's okay to
cheat in that case right so that's just
one example and there are there are
incidents in the mahabat when you could
say that Lord Krishna encouraged the
pandavas to kind of bend the rules of
warfare which is fine so he Lord Krishna
was not an idealist he was a
realist he knew that you had to win the
war
otherwise you know there'll be a really
adverse
outcome so you don't have to look
outside to understand that idealism
isn't the right
thing you just need to look at your own
history so our great leaders some of
them who were real idealists we can talk
about we can I can give you examples
like Mr Gandhi and Mr Neu idealists
especially Mr Gandhi you know turn the
other cheek
hinoda did Lord Krishna live by the the
the slogan of aimsa paroda did he but he
tried his best not to go to war he tried
his best to arrive at a diplomatic
negotiated settlement that would prevent
war from making out he was ready to
accept just five Villages for the
pandavas from the coras but even that
was not acceptable to the coras to
duryodhan So eventually Lord Krishna
said okay War it is so let's go to
war and he was the the Forefront he was
the Char charer of Arjun so Lord Krishna
himself didn't not believe in this
slogan of AA
paroda
right he tried for ainsa but at the end
of the day he went for
hinsa so if you just look at your own
history your own the example of your own
ancestors you you will you will see that
idealism doesn't work you have to be
realistic you have to be practical you
have to be pragmatic so yeah so the
great leaders for ours who tried to take
us in an idealistic Direction
they did our country our civilization
and our people a great
disservice
okay okay next question is by Santan
biswas is it true that Hinduism
destroyed sism native religion of
Manipur what was happening in Kangle
parak or Manipur during the Mahabharat
times uh did Lord Krishna Arjun bishma
Etc knew about Kang kangleipak civiliz
ation why in our history textbooks
Kangle par is not considered or shown as
a janapada but the kamrup dynasty
covering Assam mizor meala Etc is does
this mean that Kang Pak was a separate
entity in vic times as its culture may
have evolved in isolation from the rest
of India so we're talking about Manipur
here presently Manipur historically
known as Kangle Park so is it true first
of all that Hinduism destroyed sanism
the native religion of Manipur sism
still exists in
Manipur and sism is kind of syncretized
with with Gia V noism in Manipur so sism
has not been destroyed now there is this
narrative that has spread since the 20th
century that uh I forget the name of the
king who's the king okay that king of
Manipur who embraced Gia vaishnavism it
is said that that
King uh ordered the destruction through
burning of the M the manipuri sacred
text
called the puas okay this story first
appears in the 20th century after
Independence if I'm not mistaken in some
some some magazine and then it it
spreads like wildfire and it is now
accepted as universal truth by people in
Manipur that the the king of Manipur who
who
embraced Gia vaishnavism and made it the
official religion State religion he
ordered the burning of the manipuri the
M sacred books the
puas there is no truth to this there is
no primary source that that attests to
this
event but yeah it's it's accepted as as
as self-evident truth today there is no
evidence for it and Sal mahm has not
been destroyed there is there are
temples to to various gods of the sonami
pantheon in Manipur still being woried
actively so what's happened in Manipur
with the past few CES is like what
happened in
Japan when Buddhism entered Japan about
more than 1500 years ago the native
indigenous religion let's say culture of
Japan is
Shinto okay Shinto is a polytheistic
belief system there are elements of
nature worship animism ancestor worship
polytheism in chinto just like in sism
just like in
Hinduism what we call Hinduism so once
Buddhism came into Japan it came not as
Buddhism but actually as Hinduism they
still have Vic ceremonies in Japan in
various temples and all the Hindu gods
are are still worshiped in Japan so what
happened in Japan was that Shinto and
this Indian culture they got intermixed
in a beautiful syncretic culture emerged
which is still practiced to a certain
extent in Japan uh the major restoration
tried to undo that but did not really
work very successfully but yeah so the
same thing happened in Manipur
sism what we call sism and Gia
vaishnavism kind of syncretized and
today in in the houses of the mes of
manipuri Hindus you will have both
deities deities of both Traditions being
being worshipped and it's not like so so
it's incorrect to say that Hinduism
destroyed sism or any such thing but yes
the Marxist historians and certain
parties certain elements in Manipur have
tried to put forth this view this notion
that Hinduism is an invasive force in
Manipur and it is it has destroyed sism
and because of Hinduism the manipuri
king burned these sacred texts and all
that there
is no element of truth truth to that now
about the other
question uh during the Mahabharat times
did people know about kangleipak
civilization I'm not sure uh the
question then is about the origin of the
mes who are the manipuri people and from
whom the Sonam Mahi culture and the
manipuri language come what's their
origin we not quite sure because our
historians have not done any work we
know that this civilization this culture
is at least 2,000 years old we know that
the mes have been ruling Manipur for at
least 2,000 years probably more than
3,500 years but the Mahabharat probably
predates that most likely Mahabharat
happened before
that I'll not go into the dating of the
maharat okay that's a whole different
story so
so probably the ancestors of the Maes
perhaps came from somewhere else we
don't know for sure I'm just this is
pure conjecture but maybe they came from
maybe from Burma maybe from somewhere
else and settled in this region maybe
three and a half thousand years ago
that's a long long long
time so it was not a mahaj janapada and
maybe during the Mahabharat times it did
not exist possibly perhaps we don't know
so that's the thing so maybe it did not
exist during the Vic times Vic times is
even before the ramayan which is before
the Mahabharat that is like God knows
how many thousands of years ago so uh
that's why Manipur or kangleipak is not
regarded as a mahaj janapada maybe it is
a more recent occurrence a more recent
entity maybe only three and a half
thousand years old years old so when it
comes to the Indian the context of
Indian history three and a half thousand
years is is like more recent times yeah
so yeah that's what I can say about
this next question is by swapnil Mishra
how did the first Polynesians find their
way across the vast Pacific Ocean during
ancient times without any of the
nautical tools that later Navigators
used okay we're talking about
uh we're talking about the Pacific Ocean
region so let's put that on the
map the South Pacific the Polynesians
they live
mostly in the South Pacific region so we
go eastwards from India and we're now
into the Pacific Ocean region vast
enormous territory and you have all
these islands and archipelagos over here
Samoa Tonga French Polynesia Cook
Islands new
calonia and much more over here you have
hungara and these are the gal Galapagos
you have Hawaii and all that so this
entire enormous region is the Pacific
Ocean region and you have lots of these
islands over here
which are inhabited by what we call
poian Peoples now the poian peoples most
likely originated somewhere in Asia okay
uh I don't recall right now what the
studies say but the origin is most
likely Eastern
Asian um and then for some reason they
went seaf Fairing and they spread over
centuries maybe over thousands of years
years across all these islands in the
mainly in the South Pacific but also in
Hawaii
so how did this happen and why did they
go out and take such enormous risks
because this this ocean is mostly empty
let's try and find the distance between
let's say uh Fiji and Tonga what's the
distance like measure
distance it's 765 kilom so you have
hundreds of kilometers of open ocean and
you're traveling in small boats you're
traveling in canoes without triggers
so why do that and how do you navigate I
think uh the reasons for this
exploration of the ocean are lost in
time that history is lost we don't know
what compelled them or what impelled
them to go and take such enormous risks
and go out into hundreds of square
kilometers of empty ocean to find land
somewhere hopefully I don't know why
they did that how did they navigate I'm
sure they had navigation to the sun and
the stars and the Moon
that's how typically you would do
primitive
navigation uh so I think the navigation
tools were just the the celestial
objects mainly the stars and the moon uh
I'm sure people for thousands of years
have had some understanding of how the
the constellations and the stars and the
planets move in the sky so you can you
know hopefully trace a path using that
so I think it was through observation of
the Skies that they navigated but they
took enormous risks and they had no
means of knowing whether they would be
successful or not when they were first
going out to discover new lands and I'm
sure many must have perished in these
attempts but eventually many islands
most of these islands were
settled
yeah okay ABI view says have you watched
the three three body problem series why
can't we solve a three stars system I
have watched uh a couple of episodes I
have actually read the book the first
book in the series which is called the
three body problem that is a few years
ago several years ago and when the
series came out I was interested because
I I love science fiction so I watched a
couple of episodes and it wasn't that
great not bad overall but not that that
great so main thing is I have read the
first book I don't remember the entire
story the entire thing today but it's
all obviously about the tri Solaris
system this hypothetical science system
uh fictitious World in which you have a
planet that is
uh that is that is part of a three star
system so it's a three three body
problem three gravitating objects three
stars and that's the concept and
obviously it's a chaotic system it's a
chaotic system because when it comes to
solving the three body problem there are
very few stable Solutions and even the
stable Solutions can be really chaotic
so the question is why can't we solve a
three stars or three body system the
problem is very simple actually on at
face value you have three bodies in
space isolated three gravitating bodies
let's say the masses are M1 M2
M3 and they are bound together through
Newton's grav through the force of
gravitation through the let's say the
Newtonian universal law of gravitation
how will such a system evolve over time
starting from time t equal to zero and
you set them in motion
so we find that there are lots of
Solutions in which the bound State
breaks up this is essentially a bound
State problem a bound state of three
gravitating objects it's a classical
bound State Newtonian physics Newtonian
gravity and you find that in lots of
these cases the bound State simply
breaks up because the system is too
chaotic there are a few Solutions maybe
like 10 12 maybe 15 known Solutions in
which the bound state is stable but even
then it's pretty chaotic I mean the the
movement of the three objects three
three stars are are not easily
predictable they are pretty chaotic and
they weird orbits some of the orbits are
pretty symmetric nice orbits but some of
them are really elongated and and weird
and if you happen to be on a
planet around one of these Stars it's
going to be and if you have life there
it's going to be a very chaotic life so
that's what it is so it's not like we
can't solve the three star system the
problem of of the three body the it's
not like we can not solve three body
problem it's just that there are very
few actual Solutions stable solutions
that that exist most of the solutions
are unstable which means that the bound
State breaks up so the solutions are
there but there are only a handful of
Solutions in most other cases the the
bound State doesn't last it breaks up
and the Stars drift off in various
directions ad Guru Prasad says why do we
study pure
math pure Math is
Fun um so yeah why do we study pure
math most people don't study pure math
now what is pure math it's just abstract
mathematics abstract logic and it has no
actual
applications like for example
ramanujan why did he do what he
did what he was doing is you can
consider that to be pure math you can
consider what Oiler Leonard Oiler did
pure
mathematics so the real see most people
don't want to study pure math they just
don't understand what's the purpose so
it's not for everybody it's only for a
very small number of people in the world
who are fascinated by pure mathematics
and why do why do they do
it you could ask yourself why do people
write poetry why do some people want to
play music it's just because it's there
in you you have that drive that instinct
that desire to do it very few people can
be really good musicians but some people
are just driven to do music some people
are just driven to do to write
poetry similarly some people are driven
to explore and research pure mathematics
and study pure mathematics small number
of people and most of what the research
and study and whatever you do in pure
mathematics has no real
applications
apparently apparently
see ramanujan came up with all those
Fantastical equations a 100 years ago
today some of those equations are being
used to find let's say
um the Val the to compute the right
value of pi or whatever and there are
certain applications in other fields
also of ramanujan's equations one of the
fastest ways of of calculating Pi is
through one of ramanujan's equations or
or one one class of ramanujan
equations when it comes to prime numbers
the study of prime numbers seems to be
completely
abstruse you
know esoteric kind of pursuit the study
of prime numbers what's the point of
studying prime
numbers but do you know that prime
numbers are today used in
cryptography
encryption so the deal with pure math is
that it looks completely pointless
it looks like these people have their
heads high up in the in the clouds or in
the Stars they are doing research that
has no real application applications but
you may it may turn out that a century
later people will find applications of
that so the deal is it is important to
study pure mathematics no matter how
complicated no matter how pointless it
looks it will
eventually lead to certain applications
but the desire to study P Ma comes from
inside certain people very few people
have that and it's just like the desire
to write poetry or the desire to play
Beautiful music and so on that's why
people do it but it it eventually leads
to important
applications swap says what's a limnic
eruption that triggered the catastrophic
outgassing of of carbon dioxide in Lake
NEOS in Cameroon in 1986 affecting
thousands of humans in livestock a
limnic a liic eruption is when you have
a lake or a large water body suddenly
gives off a tremendous amount of carbon
dioxide of or or sometimes methane
typically carbon dioxide a certain
eruption of carbon dioxide gas from that
Lake let's say and this sudden outflow
of carbon
dioxide leads to the deaths of lots of
animals even human beings in the
vicinity of the lake because carbon
dioxide is is heavier than than
air carbon dioxide is heavier than
nitrogen and oxygen which are the which
are the main components of air so if
carbon dioxide comes out of a lake it's
going to stay down it's going not it's
not going to go up into the atmosphere
it will stay down it will blanket the
surrounding areas the surrounding
regions around the lake and because
carbon dioxide is it's it's it's lethal
if you breathe only carbon dioxide
you're going to
die so yeah that's a lmic eruption now
what causes it you know so first of all
why would carbon dioxide be dissolved in
the waters of a lake that typically
happens I would say from the
decomposition of organic material like
dead animals or dead plants the
decomposition of that can give off
carbon dioxide and sometimes volcanic
eruptions and geothermal activity can
give off can can cause carbon dioxide to
get dissolved in the waters of a lake
let's
say uh you also find that carbon dioxide
is more so
soluble in water at higher pressure so
deeper in a lake where the pressure is
pressure is higher you'll have more
carbon dioxide dissolved and also
because deeper water is colder you'll
have more carbon dioxide dissolved so
what you have is a situation like a soda
bottle take a look at this this is a
soda bottle so there is carbon dioxide
dissolved in this soda bottle all right
it's in here but it's under pressure and
the the the cap is sealed Clos now for
some reason let's say
I open this can you hear
that can you see the bubbles forming can
you see the bubbles forming here whoopsy
Daisy so there you have it this sort of
situation if it happens in a lake
there'll be certain outflow of carbon
dioxide so what could let's say you have
a lake that's completely saturated with
carbon dioxide dissolved in the water
why would such such such an eruption
suddenly happen it could happen perhaps
because of an earthquake
perhaps there's a volcanic eruption
under the under the lake or somewhere
nearby maybe there's a landslide into
the lake that certainly relas releases
all this carbon dioxide you could even
have a carbon dioxide tsunami in a lake
in that uh situation so that's what a
limic eruption is and it releases so
much carbon dioxide that it blankets the
surrounding regions killing whatever
animal life exists over there whether
it's animals or humans and apparently it
happened in Cameroon in 86 Lake Neos so
that's what a lionic eruption
is capap kapish Chri says in your
earlier video you explained about
schinger cat and you said that the cat
will continue to live forever because
every time it has two options to die or
not to die but if this theory is true
then we will be we will see a man who is
200 years old or thousand years old but
we don't see this in our universe not
not even a single case with any species
so what's the deal what I spoke about a
long long time ago I'm sure
is about uh the many the many worlds
interpretation of quantum mechanics so
let me give a very very simplistic uh uh
overview of what that
is according to the man view many worlds
many worlds interpretation of quantum
mechanics whenever you make a choice
whenever some event happens that has
multiple possible
outcomes let's let's say you make a
choice shall I wear a black shirt or a
white shirt so today let's say and you
have two shirts in front of you let's
say you chose to wear the black shirt
like I'm wearing over here but maybe I
had a white shirt and when I when I made
that choice of black versus white the my
Universal timeline split into two
universes and in the other Universe I'm
wearing a white shirt and there's a live
stream happening in a parallel universe
in which I have a white shirt on instead
of a black shirt let's say I got I was
driving a car and my car got involved in
an accident
very dangerous accident but I walked out
unscathed but when that accident
happened there are multiple
possibilities of the accident so that
broke my the world timeline into two and
in
another parallel universe I died so what
that tells you that you will have
multiple life or death death events in
in
your timeline in your life
and whenever that happens the timeline
splits into
two and in the one that you die your
Consciousness doesn't survive so you're
not aware of it but in the one that you
stay alive you're aware of it so you
will always
find according to if the manal the
manal's interpretation is correct you
will find that you you personally keep
on living forever you never die and
eventually you will be in a situation
where you are the oldest being alive in
the universe
and you will find that all other beings
are younger than you because this is the
rarest case so it's kind of like that
it's it's called Quantum
immortality so every time there's the
situation you die and you not die at the
same time but wherever the the world in
which you have died your Consciousness
won't survive there so you will not be
aware of it so it feels like it seems to
you that that people around you die once
in a while people grow old and die
people have whatever thing and die but
you stay alive
forever so that's the kind of thing it
is it's called Quantum immortality some
people call it quantum hell because you
will never die and you will get older
and older and older eventually you're
the oldest being alive in the
universe so every person inhabits a
special Universe of their own
essentially that's that's how you could
kind of put
it yeah that's that's what it
is okay Rik says it is said that we
never physically contact with anyone or
anything at a microscopic level then why
do clapping and similar activities
produce sound if we are never in touch
physically yes physical touch is
actually impossible let's say a clap so
yeah my hands do come together you feel
the sensation of the two hands coming
together but are are the two hands
actually touching at the quantum level
it's atoms right is atoms inside and if
you know what an atom is like you have
the nucleus which is protons and
neutrons in the center and out outside
in in these shells or orbits or orbitals
whatever you want to call it you have
electrons which are negatively charged
so when two atoms come together the
outsides are negatively charged and they
will repel each other that is
electrostatic repulsion that is the
electromagnetic force and the repulsion
caused by that so two atoms will never
really touch even if they
interact never really touch and even
when atoms
form bonds molecular bonds and they come
together as molecules like NaCl sodium
chloride even then they don't really
touch nothing touches the only case in
which atoms really touch in when is when
you have nuclear a nuclear reaction when
nuclear come together and actually
touch so when I touch like this there's
no nuclear reaction happening here so
it's not really touch it's the Sensation
that you get because of electrostatic
because of of the electromagnet IC Force
the repulsive
Force which comes from electromagnetism
and there's also power's Exclusion
Principle and all that are involved
which because of which matter occupies
space and all that so there is no real
touch then how does clapping happen how
does sound happen well clapping sound
all of that is not a Quantum phenomenon
it's a classical phenomenon so we have
to look at it entirely classically and
don't don't look at it from the quantum
perspective there's no quantum theory of
sound sound is a classical phenomenon
and you can't really explain it from the
perspective of quantum mechanics so yeah
so as far as we are concerned we are we
touch you know this is this is touch but
at at the quantum level there's no touch
there's no real touching unless there's
a nuclear reaction you don't you don't
want your touch to produce nuclear
reactions do you so yeah it's because of
because because the quantum domain is so
different from the classical domain that
we are familiar with but somehow the
classical domain
emerges from the quantum World in ways
that we don't completely understand yeah
very strange the world is the universe
is a strange strange
place okay indrajit says what are your
thoughts on primordial black holes some
papers that there are no some papers say
that these are micro black holes and
these are responsible for dark matter I
would be aware of that would I not
be uh also I wonder how the matter was
compressed below the schwat chill radius
to form them if they exist or is there
some other way so what are primordial
black holes primordial black
holes we know the Big Bang happened all
our evidence all the data tells us that
something like a big bang would have
happened which is the sudden expansion
of SpaceTime it was not an explosion it
was the expansion of
SpaceTime now in the very early Universe
the universe was very small very very
very strong and you have Quantum
fluctuations
which is which comes from the which
comes from Quantum field Theory we know
they exist Quantum fluctuations we know
they they happen okay it's known so when
you have Quantum fluctuations in such an
incredibly compressed
Universe you will have regions of high
density of space time and low density of
space time of energy and in some places
where you have high enough
density the density will will be so much
that it will produce black hole but the
black holes will be so small that
they'll be microscopic so those are
ordal black holes and there are lots of
models of the early Universe in which
there is an over production of these
microscopic primordial black holes so
most likely these primordial black holes
did exist most likely we have never seen
one but most likely they would have been
produced in the very early Universe are
they still around well that's that's an
open question are some of their
artifacts still around in some form
maybe maybe possibly so uh and yeah if
they are still around or if bound states
of primordial black holes are still
around they could be responsible for
Dark Matter possibly yes I would know uh
the question is how was the matter
compressed below the schat radius what
is the schatell radius in the first
place uh the the swash the SW SK radius
is
the uh is the is what defines the
Horizon outer Horizon of a black hole
um 2 mg by c^2 2 mg by c^ 2 mass times
the gravitational constant divid by the
square of the speed of light that is the
SCH Shield
radius now in the case of micro black
holes which exists at the quantum level
in the quantum domain the schwar black
the schwar radius simply doesn't apply
because it
is an artifact that comes out of general
relativity which breaks down the quantum
level so how can a a primordial micro
black hole which is a Quantum sized
black hole have a short chill radius it
can't so you have to treat it
differently there should be a different
kind of radius that applies to it but
how would it be compressed to that level
because in the very early universe
everything was so small and so
compressed that it was it was really
easy really easy to compress matter into
its wat shilled radius so my thoughts on
primordial black holes are that if they
do exist and if some of their artifacts
bound States or whatever still exists
then they could certainly account for
dark matter and um I think it's pretty
likely that primordial black holes did
exist and they did form in the very
early universe that that's my view about
that okay Kush anushirvan says I am a
student metaphorically and I want to
learn advanced mathematics physics
history computer science economics and
solve complex problems however whenever
I try to learn I get bogged down either
by procrastination or I develop
self-pity whenever I try to compare
myself to others and I find it hard to
be consistent please help
me okay the first thing
is you want to learn any subject to an
advanced
level takes time takes a lot of uh Focus
time patience and effort and you also
need to have the aptitude for the
subject and then you can't learn
advanced computer science Advanced
physics Advanced economics Advanced
history all at the same time it's not
possible it's not possible you have to
pick one field and you work on that so
let's say you want to learn Advanced
physics well you start with mathematics
because you won't be able to learn
anything about Advanced physics without
First Learning the requisite
mathematics so you have to go
through High School level mathematics
then college level mathematics
then more advanced mathematics then you
to go through books like the ones I have
behind which will then help you learn
Advanced physics so it would take you
two to three years I would say of
properly learning advanced
mathematics maybe two years if you study
diligently several hours a day and you
solve a gazillion problems that's how
you learn mathematics if you do that
then you'll be able to start learning
Advanced physics But first you to master
basic physics you know H rest kind of
stuff and then you go into more advanced
stuff so it takes time it's not easy
takes time so first of all you can't
learn advanced mathematics physics
economics computer science all of that
at the same time you you have to focus
on one
thing and secondly it'll take you it'll
take you time if you want to become
really good at understanding history it
will take you a long time you read lots
and lots and lots read everything
possible read yeah
so it's a it's a long-term Journey it's
it's like it's like bodybuilding you
want to you want to bulk up and become
what do they call it ripped yolked
whatever you start today it's going to
take you at least two years and you have
to be at it every day at least five days
a week and take care of your diet take
care of your sleep work out with a
proper work workout program and so on
it's just like that lots of patience
lots of
determination and focus and consistency
all of that
so procrastination could happen because
you're trying to focus on too many
things at the same time self-pity um if
you want to come look there's no point
comparing yourself to others ever always
compare yourself to who you used to be
until yesterday and ask yourself One S
single
question am I proud of
myself and uh whatever I did today does
it make me proud of proud of myself
that's the kind of thing you need to
have and you have to keep on doing it
consistently there's no point comparing
your yourself to others compare yourself
with the previous version of yourself
and try to become way better than what
you are today that's what you have to do
and yeah consistency and
focus uh pratik Singh says what happens
after death in terms of soul and
Consciousness are we just a lot of atoms
which learns how to think talk breathe
eat Etc through through stimulus around
us look I don't know what happens after
death because
I'm alive I haven't experienced it so
Consciousness I don't know but think of
it like
this you have a birthday all of you who
are watching you have a
birthday day month
year let's say you were born on the 1st
of
January
okay where were you one year before that
where were
you were you did you exist so thinking
about death is exactly the
same as thinking about before you were
born before you were conceived did your
soul exist
somewhere did your Consciousness exist
somewhere if it did then why don't you
remember anything so we don't have the
answers to these questions okay so I
cannot answer these questions I am not
some great highly attained
spiritual person I'm just a regular
person over here so I don't have the
answers when it comes to Soul
Consciousness we don't know what
Consciousness is we're trying to figure
it out but far from that there's a big
mysteries in life and that's what makes
life interesting because it's so
mysterious okay I've taken a lot of
questions about 28 29 30 questions now
let me take some questions for a few
minutes from the live
chat live
chat okay I'm going to take a few
questions from the live chat maybe three
or four questions so if you have
something okay om beer says suggest a
good book to study quantum mechanics
well I don't know where you are in
quantum mechanics study right now are
you a complete beginner are you
intermediate level or whatever so if you
are a complete beginner and if you have
if you have a decent understanding of
mathematics like basic uh you know
college level calculus and linear
algebra all that then I would uh suggest
Griffiths quantum mechanics by Griffiths
that's the first step you should take if
you have a decent understanding of
mathematics quantum mechanics by
Griffiths once you done with Griffiths
you move on to zti Quantum Mechanics by
zti and then you move on to other books
as well so I I'll suggest the first book
The introductory book is Griffiths g r i
f fi T HS that's where typically
everybody starts once you're done with
that you move on to ztd z e TT i l i or
something like that I have it somewhere
over here behind yeah so that's book
number one and book number two but for
that you need a decent understanding of
mathematics all
right uh did you watch UFC 300 Max
versus Justin was just crazy I did not
watch it I was on a trip somewhere work
trip always working I didn't watch it
but I did see The
Knockout uh Max holay versus Justin gage
g yeah just Stand and Deliver right both
were at it and then one punch takes out
Justin gii yeah I I wish I had watched
it but unfortunately I did
not okay let's take some other questions
just a few
more
um okay Karan nwat says is the Indian
tech tectonic plate breaking apart you
know that's not how tectonic plates
plates work there are the subduction
zones and all plate tectonics is pretty
complex it's like the crust of the
inside below the Earth you have this
liquid this thick viscous liquid called
magma and below the magma you have an
outer core which is solid and an inner
core which is even more solid something
like that something like that okay and
this magma which is all thick and
viscous and liquid it's it's molten rock
and higher than that you have the crust
the mantle in the crust which is solid
now because the magma is always flowing
around inside that's why the crust also
moves around and that's what causes
subduction and all these tectonic plates
the tectonic plates typically slide
under other tectonic plates and it is
the these movements that cause
earthquakes and that is what has caused
India the subcontinent to break free
from Africa and Madagascar and slam into
Eurasia which lifted up the Himalayan
Mountains so it is not breaking apart it
is still slamming into Eurasia that's
what's happening right
now okay
maybe one or two
questions uh yeah one again AR Gotham
says do you follow IPL once in a while I
will just put the TV on and see what's
happening right now I don't really
follow
it um I don't no time first of all and
secondly it doesn't really doesn't
really interest me that much like let's
say a test match between India and
Australia for example IPL doesn't
doesn't really enjoy me I mean I mean
interest me that much it's just a six
hitting
Fest I like to see Bowlers on top I like
to see the ball swing I like to see
Bowlers I like to you know there's no
nothing more interesting and exciting
like a low scoring game in which the
Wicket is difficult and both sides are
struggling to score and you have a low
score and it's difficult to reach that
low score that's more exciting in my
opinion than everybody hitting sexcess
with their eyes closed so nothing
against the IPL I used to as a kid I
used used to really I played Cricket to
a certain level and I used to enjoy
watching Cricket these days IPL I don't
have the of the time and somehow I don't
find it that interesting
anymore right okay what
else rajit star says why is IPL batting
dominant now or Cricket in
itself flat pitches you create flat
pitches it's going to be easy the ball
doesn't spin much the ball doesn't
bounce much the ball doesn't swing much
you can just see the line of the wall
and hit through the line and you have
all these these new bats which which are
so which send the ball so far
away so it's because of flat pitches and
because people love to see sixes and
fours so that's why they've made it like
that so that's why it is so batting
dominant like somebody just
said there you have it more sixes more
viewers
yeah Nan Jen says India is planning to
send Mann missions to the Moon by 2040
My Views I think it's a little we need
to be a little more ambitious let's end
it by 2035 we need to have a presence on
the
moon so I have a video about how we
should do it and I said that that chra
and 10 should send humans to the Moon by
2035 that's what I had said but yeah we
have a plan for 2040 well not bad let's
do it and let's make it happen so I'm
I'm happy happy about it I'm I'm really
glad that we have that Vision that we
need to have Indian BS on the ground on
the Moon by 2040 good job I I would like
to see that happen and I would like to
see progress in that
direction okay let's take one last
question herel says vote turnout was
really poor do you think it's bad for
the N yeah the first phase of election
for of voting the voter turnout was kind
of concerning it was kind of less and
when the vter turnout is less it's kind
of concerning for the incumbent party I
hope it gets better I obviously want to
see Mr Modi come back to Power okay so
in case you're wondering whom to vote
for vote for Narendra Modi all right all
right that's it for today thank you so
much once again for watching I I really
appreciate all your questions I
appreciate your viewership I apologize
to those of you whose questions I could
not take I had so many questions in the
comments I I was only able to take about
30 of those I think roughly and lots of
questions in the chat over here but so
next time I'll keep on doing these live
streams more now and I'll take as many
questions as possible so thank you so
much for watching take care have a good
day good night wherever you are and keep
raising your standards until next time